Coconut cream pie!

Pie crust:

1 cup very cold butter cut into small cubes

2 ½ cups flour

½ tsp salt

1/4 cup to 1/3 ice water, Only enough to make a dough form.

Coconut cream filling

3 cups whole milk

1/3 cup flour

2/3 cup sugar

pinch of salt

1 cup unsweetened fine coconut

3 slightly beaten extra large egg yolks

4 tbsp butter

2 tsp vanilla extract

1/4 tsp pure almond extract

Vanilla whipped cream

1 cup whipping cream

1 tsp vanilla extract

3 tbsp icing sugar, powdered sugar

Instructions

Pie crust (makes 2)

Using a food processor or a pastry blender cut cold butter into flour and salt until mixture resembles a coarse meal. Small pieces of butter should still be visible.

Pour cold water over the mixture and work in by tossing with a fork until dough begins to form. Use your hands as little as possible and work the dough as little as possible.

Divide dough into 2 balls, flatten into 2 rounds, wrap in plastic wrap and place in the refrigerator to rest for a minimum of 20 minutes. You can freeze the second round for another time.

You can make your dough the previous day but make sure you take it out of the fridge for 10 -20 minutes to warm slightly before rolling out.

Roll the dough into a 12 inch round and place in the bottom of a 10 inch pie plate.

Trim and flute the edges as desired.

Poke a few holes in the bottom of the pastry shell, rest in the refrigerator for an additional 20 minutes before baking at 400 degrees F for 12 – 15 minutes or until golden brown.

Cool completely before adding the filling.

Coconut cream filling

Scald the milk in the microwave or on the stove top to almost boiling. Microwave works best as there is no chance of burning the milk.

Meanwhile, in a saucepan combine the flour, sugar, salt and coconut.

Over medium low flame slowly add 1 cup of the scalded milk, whisking constantly.

As you notice the filling beginning to thicken, add another cup of the scalded milk continuing to stir constantly until it begins to thicken again.

Add the final cup of scalded milk, stirring constantly. Continue to cook over medium low heat until mixture begins to slightly thicken.

At this point remove from heat and pour about a half cup of this mixture onto the beaten egg yolks, whisking constantly.

Pour the egg mixture immediately back into the pot, continuing to constantly stir.

Cook for an additional two or three until the filling reaches pudding consistency and remove from the flame. The mixture should just be beginning to boil at this point.

Stir in the butter, vanilla and almond extract.

Cool for about 20 minutes before pouring into the baked pie shell/s.

Chill the pie/s completely for several hours or overnight before adding the vanilla whipped cream.

Vanilla whipped cream

Combine the whipping cream, icing sugar and vanilla extract and beat to soft peaks. Spread on top of the cooled coconut cream filling. Garnish with toasted coconut and serve.

Recipe from: https://www.rockrecipes.com/coconut-cream-pie/

Grandma Moog's Gingersnap Cookies from: Penzey's Spices

Ingredients

2 Cups flour

2 tsp. baking soda

1/4 tsp. salt

3/4 Cup butter (or vegetable shortening)

1 Cup sugar

1 large egg

1/4 Cup molasses

1 tsp. GINGER, powdered

1 tsp. CINNAMON, powdered

1/2 tsp. CLOVES, powdered

1/3 Cup granulated sugar (to roll dough in)

Directions

Sift flour, baking soda and salt together, set aside.

In a large mixing bowl, beat shortening and sugar until well blended. Beat in egg, molasses, GINGER, CINNAMON, and CLOVES.

Add the flour mixture in two parts, blending well.

Shape the dough into a ball, cover and refrigerate overnight or at least 2 hours. Preheat oven to 350°.

Shape dough into 1 1/2-inch balls. Roll the balls thoroughly in sugar, place on ungreased cookie trays.

The cookies spread out during baking, so don’t crowd them. Bake 15 minutes.

Cool for a minute, then remove from cookie sheets. Store in an airtight container for crispy cookies, or in a regular cookie jar for chewy cookies.

Prep. time: 10 minutes plus chilling; Baking time: 30 minutes total (2 sheets at a time for 15 minutes each) Yield: 50-60 cookies

Nutritional Information Servings 30; Serving Size 2 cookies (28g); Calories 130; Calories from fat 50; Total fat 5g; Cholesterol 5mg; Sodium 105mg; Carbohydrate 19g; Dietary Fiber 0g; Sugars 12g; Protein 1g.

Rolled Flank steak From: “The Mediterranean Diet Cookbook”, Rockridge Press, 2013

Ingredients:

2 pounds flank steak

Salt and freshly ground black pepper

1 Tablespoon olive oil

1/4 cup onion, diced

1 clove garlic, minced

2 cups baby spinach, chopped

1/2 cup dried tomatoes, chopped (if using tomatoes in oil, save the oil and use for the saute)

1/2 cup roasted red bell pepper, diced

1/2 cup almonds, roasted and finely chopped

Kitchen twine

1/2 cup chicken stock

Preparation:

Lay the flank steak out on a cutting board and season with salt and pepper.

Heat the olive oil (and sun-dried tomato oil) in a medium saucepan. Add the onion and garlic.

Cook for 5 minutes over medium heat, stirring frequently, till onion is tender and translucent.

Add the spinach, tomatoes, peppers and almonds, and cook and additional 3 minutes, or until the spinach wilts slightly.

Let the tomato and spinach mixture cool to room temperature.

Spread the tomato and spinach mixture evenly over the flank steak.

Roll the flank steak up slowly, lengthwise, and tie it securely with twine on both ends and in the middle.

Brown the flank steak on all sides in the same pan.

Place steak in slow cooker with the chicken stock, cover, and cook on low for 4-6 hours.

Slice into rounds and discard the twine.

Gado-Gado

By Hetty McKinnon (in NYT) 7-8-21 YIELD6 to 8 servings TIME45 minutes

Gado-gado is a beloved dish across Indonesia. Each region has a different spin: In Jakarta, it is a “double-carb” dish, featuring both potato and lontong (rice cakes). In West Java, it is known as lotek atah or karedok and served with raw vegetables. At the heart of any gado-gado is the spicy peanut sauce: Some versions call for tamarind, lime, terasi (shrimp paste) or coconut milk. Others use peanut butter instead of freshly pounded peanuts. This particular recipe is inspired by a home-cooked gado-gado eaten in Bali, where the rich, aromatic sauce was powered by shallots and garlic. Its sweetness comes from kecap manis, the thick, caramelly soy sauce foundational in Indonesian cooking, but, if you can’t find kecap manis, make your own (see Tip) or use sweet soy sauce.

INGREDIENTS

FOR THE SALAD: 2 to 3 tablespoons neutral oil, such as grapeseed or vegetable 1 (14-ounce) package extra-firm tofu, drained and cut into 1/2-inch slices Kosher salt and freshly ground pepper 10 ounces green beans, trimmed ½ small Napa cabbage, finely sliced 6 ounces bean sprouts (about 2 cups) 10 new potatoes or other small variety, peeled and halved 1 large cucumber, peeled and sliced thinly on the diagonal 2 tomatoes, each cut into 8 wedges 4 boiled (8-minute) eggs, peeled and halved ½ cup homemade or store-bought fried shallots

FOR THE SATAY SAUCE: 1 cup roasted unsalted peanuts 4 shallots, peeled and sliced 3 garlic cloves, sliced 1 to 2 red chiles, deseeded and sliced 3 tablespoons kecap manis (see Tip) 2 tablespoons palm or brown sugar 1 teaspoon sea salt

PREPARATION Heat a large frying pan over medium-high. When hot, drizzle with 1 to 2 tablespoons oil and add the tofu slices. Season the tofu well with salt and pepper. Reduce heat to medium and fry for 2 to 3 minutes on each side until golden brown. Remove from the pan and allow to cool. Cut tofu into squares or triangles. Bring a large pot of salted water to a boil. Add green beans and blanch for about 4 minutes or until just tender. Just before the beans are ready, add cabbage and bean sprouts to the pot and shock them in the water for about 30 seconds to 1 minute. Transfer the vegetables to a colander, refresh under cold water and drain well. Bring the same pot of water (add more water and salt, if required) to the boil, and add the potatoes and cook until tender, about 15 minutes.

Meanwhile, make the satay sauce: Place the peanuts, sliced shallots, garlic and chile into a blender or food processor, and blitz until it becomes a chunky paste. You can add a splash of water to get the blender going, or if you prefer a smoother paste. (It is traditional to use a mortar and pestle to make the paste, so if you have one, use it.)

Heat a medium saucepan over medium-low, drizzle with remaining 1 tablespoon oil, and add the paste, stirring constantly, for 2 to 3 minutes, until fragrant. Add the kecap manis, palm sugar, salt and 1 cup water. Stir for 2 to 3 minutes, until the sauce is well combined. (Peanut sauce can be stored in a jar in the refrigerator for 7 days.) To serve, divide the blanched vegetables, potatoes, tofu, cucumber, tomatoes and eggs over several serving plates or assemble it all on one large serving platter. Drizzle each plate generously with the peanut sauce and top with crispy fried shallots.

Tip You can make your own substitute for kecap manis by mixing together equal amounts of soy sauce and palm sugar (or brown sugar) and boiling until syrupy, 10 to 15 minutes. Allow to cool completely, as it will thicken further. Store in the refrigerator for up to 4 weeks.

Spinach and Gruyère Breakfast Casserole By Melissa Clark Updated Dec. 19, 2023

Total Time 1 hour 50 minutes, plus at least 8 hours chilling and 10 minutes resting Prep Time 10 minutes Cook Time 1 hour 40 minutes, plus at least 8 hours chilling and 10 minutes resting

Like most of its kind, you can assemble the casserole the day before you want to bake it, then pop it in the oven an hour or so before serving. It will emerge puffed and golden on top, ready for its star-turn on any festive table.

INGREDIENTS

8 ounces baguette or other crusty bread, cut into 1 ½-inch cubes

6 tablespoons unsalted butter

1 teaspoon kosher salt (such as Diamond Crystal), more as needed

2 leeks, trimmed, halved and thinly sliced into half-moons

10 ounces fresh spinach

¼ teaspoon grated nutmeg

Large pinch of ground cayenne

1 teaspoon finely grated lemon zest

2 tablespoons dry vermouth or white wine

8 large eggs

2 cups half-and-half (or use a mix of milk and heavy cream)

½ teaspoon freshly cracked black pepper

4 ounces Gruyère, grated (2 cups)

¾ cup grated Parmesan

PREPARATION

Step 1: Heat oven to 350 degrees. Lightly butter a 9-by-13-inch baking dish or a large gratin dish.

Step 2: Spread baguette cubes on a baking sheet. Bake until crisp, about 8 to 10 minutes. Transfer cubes to a large bowl and toss with 4 tablespoons melted butter and a pinch of salt.

Step 3: Meanwhile, in a large sauté pan, melt the remaining 2 tablespoons butter over medium-high heat. Add leeks and a pinch of salt, and sauté until tender and lightly golden, about 5 minutes.

Step 4: Stir in about half of the spinach leaves, a pinch of salt, nutmeg, cayenne and lemon zest, and stir until wilted, about 2 to 4 minutes. Stir in remaining spinach and another pinch of salt. Sauté until most of the liquid has evaporated, about 5 minutes longer. Stir in the vermouth and let cook for 2 to 4 minutes, or until the pan looks dry. Taste and add more salt if needed. Let spinach cool.

Step 5: In a medium bowl, whisk together eggs, half-and-half, pepper and 1 teaspoon salt. Add mixture to the baguette, tossing well. Add spinach, 1¾ cups Gruyère and ½ cup Parmesan, and toss everything until mixed (your hands work well for this).

Step 6: Pour mixture into prepared baking dish, cover, and refrigerate for 8 hours or overnight.

Step 7: When ready to bake, heat oven to 350 degrees. Uncover and top casserole with remaining ¼ cup grated Gruyère and ¼ cup grated Parmesan. Bake for 50 to 60 minutes, or until the center is set and no longer liquidy (it might puff, and that’s fine). Let sit for 10 to 20 minutes before serving.

How to make tiramisu – recipe

Wed 29 Sep 2021 07.00 EDT

238 Jonathan Coe was once “politely” reprimanded by an Italian journalist for sending a character in his novel Expo 58 to a Soho trattoria for lasagne and tiramisu, a year before (depending on who you believe) the boozy dessert first appeared on menus in northern Italy. Soothingly creamy, but spiked with coffee, this little pick-me-up (as its name translates) is a true modern classic.

Prep 35 min Chill 4 hr+ Serves 6-8

100ml strong coffee (see step 1) 4 eggs 75g caster sugar 450g mascarpone 2 tbsp sweet marsala (optional) 2 tbsp dark rum (optional) 16-24 savoiardi biscuits (or boudoir), depending on the size of your dish Cocoa powder, to dust

1 Make the coffee fff Espresso is ideal, because you want the coffee to have as intense a flavour as possible, but if you don’t have the wherewithal at home, a strongly brewed cafetiere, moka or filter pot, or even a cup of instant, will do, as will a takeaway from your favourite coffee shop if you don’t.

2 Separate the eggs Separate the eggs into two large, clean bowls – you’ll be beating the whites into a foam, so it’s important they’re not contaminated with any yolk, which might interfere with the process. As such, I’d advise cracking each white into a small bowl first, so you can make sure of this before you add it to the larger bowl.

3 Whip the egg whites Whisk the whites until they form stiff, rather than droopy peaks – you should be able to hold the bowl upside down with confidence, though be careful when testing this.

(Don’t be tempted to keep whisking after they reach this stage, because they’ll quickly start to break down into a watery mess, and you’ll need to whisk in a fresh white to get them back.) Set aside.

4 Mix the yolks with sugar Beat the egg yolks with the sugar until voluminous and pale yellow in colour; like whipping the egg whites, this is easiest done with a food mixer or electric beaters. Drain off any excess liquid from the mascarpone, if necessary, put it into a medium bowl and beat with a wooden spoon to loosen a little.

5 Mix the yolks and mascarpone Beat the cheese into the egg yolks a little at a time, until you have a smooth mixture without any lumps – with such a simple dessert, it’s worth taking your time, but try not to be too violent or you’ll lose the air you’ve just whipped into the yolks and sugar.

6 Add the whisked whites Using a large metal spoon, gently fold a third of the whisked whites into the cheese mixture, then, once that’s well combined, fold in the rest, again being careful to knock out as little air from the mix as possible. (The pudding will still be edible if it’s a bit flat, or indeed lumpy, but it won’t be as deliciously light.)

7 Now for the coffee (and booze) Put the coffee and alcohol, if using, into a wide dish. Booze doesn’t appear in all versions of tiramisu, but it does make it a more interesting dish. Feel free to adjust to taste: I’d suggest combining something sweet and something strong – sweet sherry or a liqueur such as amaretto or triple sec instead of marsala, and brandy or grappa instead of rum).

8 Soak the biscuits Dip each biscuit – savoiardi, available from larger supermarkets and Italian specialists, are best, because they’re drier and lighter than boudoir biscuits or trifle sponges, but use whatever you can find – into the coffee mixture until they’re a pale brown colour, and then use them to line the base of a medium serving bowl.

9 Layer, chill, then dust with cocoa Spoon a third of the mascarpone mixture on top of the biscuits, followed by a generous sprinkle of cocoa.

Repeat the layers twice more, finishing with a layer of the cheese mix. Cover and refrigerate for four to six hours before serving, though you can make it a day ahead, if necessary, before ending with a final flourish of cocoa dusted on top.